Mayank Joshi

Data Scientist

Data Scientist with 5+ years of experience in building data-intensive applications, overcoming complex architectural and scalability issues in diverse industries. Proficient in predictive modelling, data processing and data mining algorithms, as well as scripting languages, including Python and R. Capable of creating, developing, testing and deploying highly adaptive diverse services to translate business and functional qualifications into substantial deliverables.



joshimayank984@gmail.com



+971 0509324639



Dubai,UAE



linkedin.com/in/joshimayank7

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Machine Learning

Deep Learning

Gen Al

Data Vizualization

Inferential Statistics

Microsoft Azure

Databricks

SOL

Python

R

Tableau

LANGUAGES

English

Native or Bilingual Proficiency

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Developed a scraping tool using Scrapy, Beautiful Soup (Python libraries) to scrape Product metadata and Price to assist a Beauty Products company to price competitively against their competitors.

Built a GPT-3.5 Backed Customer Support Chatbot using Python, lLamaIndex library andOpenAI API

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist Apparel Group

10/2022 - Present Dubai, UAE

- Developed an Auto-replenishment engine and deployed for 25+ brands, optimizing and enhancing inventory management. Transitioned from a "sell one, get one" to demand forecast-based replenishment, slashing replenishment frequency from 7 to 2 times a week hence saving transportation cost. Boosted store availability from 75% to 90-95%, resulting in sales uplift of AED 8.6 Million in YTD 2024 and Loss of Sale reduction 15% to 3% while also contributing to AED 600K in labor cost savings.
- Developed a Demand Forecasting engine for RITUALS, a home and body products brand, transitioning from traditional rate-of-sale (ROS) based forecasting to a machine learning (ML) driven approach. This solution significantly reduced human labor employed to gather data, forecast and finalize the buying quantities for each product from 16 hours (2 days) to just 2 hours, and improved forecast accuracy from around 56% to 70-80% for the top 80% of sales-contributing products.
- Designed and Deployed website using Python Streamlit as a centralized platform for accessing supply chain solutions developed by the data science team, including Replenishment, Allocation, Pricing, and more. This platform not only provides stakeholders with real-time access to key performance indicators (KPIs) but also serves as a confidence-building tool for brands, fostering trust and increasing the adoption of our solutions.

Data Scientist Chalhoub Group

02/2022 - 10/2022 Dubai,UAE

- Developed Inventory and Distribution Dashboard for top management, offering real-time visibility into stock and logistics. Tracked KPIs such as Inventory Turnover, Order Fulfillment Time, and On-Time Delivery. Enhanced decision-making with data viz for trend analysis and boosting operational efficiency.
- Developed an Auto Inter-store Transfer Engine harnessing product-location sales probability estimation. This
 solution reduced Store-Store Product consolidation task completion time from 8 hours to just 30 minutes,
 magnifying operational efficiency while also bringing in a 2-3% sales uplift.

Junior Data Scientist Maytronics

02/2021 - 02/2022 Gurugram,Haryana

Developed a water pH, free chlorine (FCl), and algae level prediction engine using XGBoost. This model offers users indicators to determine whether pool water is clean or requires cleaning by the water cleaning robot.

Data Analyst

Colgate Palmolive Pvt. Ltd.

08/2018 - 02/2021 Mumbai,India

- Developed a product classification model using MultiClass Classification ML algorithms to classify local product names to global names. Reduced task time from 8 hours to just 20 minutes with an accuracy of 88%.
- Developed a Tweet tracking module (Python Dash Application) using Python, aiding the Social Media Risk Monitoring team in gauging public sentiments on specific product launches or Colgate overall.

EDUCATION

Masters of Business Management (Business Analytics) Sri Balaji University (2017-2019), Maharashtra, India

Bachelors of Science

Kerala University (2013-2016), Kerala, India